Finding Aid for the Alexander Graham Bell Collection LSC.0308
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alexander Graham Bell collection
1880-1925
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0308
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Alexander Graham Bell (1847-1922) was born in Edinburgh, Scotland. He was granted patents in 1874 on a multiple telegraph, invented the telephone (1875) and the photophone (1880). The collection consists of works by and about Alexander Graham Bell. Includes pamphlets, reprints, proceedings, portraits and geneological information compiled by Bell and others.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 999643683606533
Biography
Bell was born on March 3, 1847 in Edinburgh, Scotland; attended Edinburgh University; became assistant in London to his father, who originated phonetic visible speech system for teaching the deaf; his father moved the family to Canada in 1870; from 1873-77 Bell served as a professor of vocal physiology at Boston University; he was granted patents in 1874 on a multiple telegraph for sending two or more messages simultaneously over the same wire; invented telephone, 1875; in 1880 he patented the photophone; his laboratory in Braddock Bay, Nova Scotia turned out hydrofoil speedboats and aerial locomotion by way of kites; Bell served Clarke School for the Deaf at Northampton, Massachusetts for 51 years as teacher, researcher and president of the board; founding member of the National Geographic Society in 1888, and president, 1898-1903; he died in Braddock Bay, August 2, 1922.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of works by and about Alexander Graham Bell. Includes pamphlets, reprints, proceedings, portrait of Bell, Bell's letter to the Attorney General and one letter to Bell. Contains a first draft typescript of Catherine Mackenzie's book, Alexander Graham Bell (1928). Publications document Bell's experiments and interests in a variety of fields, including sheep breeding, eugenics, binaural audition, vocal physiology, aerial locomotion, and the telephone. Also includes geneological information compiled by Bell and others.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Bells of St. Andrews (genealogical).
Letters.
Catherine Mackenzie manuscript on Alexander Graham Bell.
Material regarding Bell's experiments and inventions.
Inventors -- United States -- Archives.; Bell, Alexander Graham; Bell, Alexander Graham -- Archives; Bell family.; Mackenzie, Catherine
- 1. Langdon, W.C. The Growth of the Historical Collection Reprinted from the issue of the Bell Telephone Quarterly., April 1925; Pamphlet (Folder 5)
- 2. The National Geographic Magazine. vol.14 no.6, Washington, D.C., June 1903. (Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents note
  Tetrahedral Principle in Kite Structure.
- 3. Alexander Graham Bell, Discovery And Invention., Pamphlet (Folder 4)
  Reprinted from the National Geographic Magazine, June 1914. Press of Judd & Detweiler, Incorporated. Washington, D.C.
- 4. From the records of Alexander Graham Bell, Sex-Determination in Sheep., Pamphlet; 2 copies. (Folder 4)
  Reprinted from the Journal of Heredity. vol.5 no.2, Washington D.C. February 1914.
- 5. Alexander Graham Bell, Utility of Action And Gesture. (Folder 4)
  Reprinted from the Volta Review, for January 1915. Washington D.C., The Volta Bureau.
- 6. Photograph: Dr. Bell. (Folder 6)
- 7. Alexander Graham Bell, Who Shall Inherit Long Life?, Pamphlet (Folder 4)
  Reprinted from the National Geographic Magazine. June 1919. Washington D.C. Press of Judd & Detweiler, Incorporated.
- 8. Alexander Graham Bell, The Mystic Oral School - An Argument in its Favor. Washington, D.C., Gibson Brothers, Printers & Bookbinders., 1897.; Pamphlet (Folder 4)
- 9. Alexander Graham Bell, A Few Thoughts Concerning Eugencies., Pamphlet (Folder 4)
  Reprinted from the National Geographic Magazine, February 1908. Washington, D.C., Press of Judd & Detweiler, Incorporated.
- 10. Readings in Line Writing., Autographed by Alexander Graham Bell. (Folder 5)
- 11. Photograph by Bell of man looking at Sheep., October 2, 1909. (Folder 6)
- 12. The National Geographic Magazine vol.19 no.1, Washington, D.C. Hubbard Memorial Hall, January 1908. 1907. (Folder 5)
- 13. The Bells of St. Andrews. (Folder 1)
  Births, Marriages & Deaths of persons of the name of Bell; from the records of St. Andrews, Scotland. Compiled by Alexander Graham Bell.
- 14. Alexander Graham Bell, Experiments Relating to Binaural Audition. (Folder 4)
  Reprinted from the American Journal of Otology, July 1880. New York: Trow's Printing & Bookbinding Company.
- 15. Alexander Graham Bell, Upon the Electrical Experiments to Determine the Location of the Bullet In the Body of the Late President Garfield, And upon A Successful Form of Induction Balance for the Painless Detection of Metallic Masses in the Human Body., 1882. (Folder 4)
  With the Author's Compliments. Washington, D.C. Gibson Brothers, Printers.
- 16. Pound, Arthur, The Telephone Idea. New York, Greenberg, Publisher, 1926. (Folder 5)
- 17. Alexander Graham Bell, Prizes for the Inventor Some of the Problems Awaiting Solution., Pamphlet (Folder 4)
- 18. Nutting, William Washburn, The 'HD-4' A 70-Miler With Remarkable Possibilities Developed At Dr. Graham Bell's laboratories on the Bras D'or Lakes., 1921.; Pamphlet (Folder 5)
  From the Smithsonian Report for 1919, Pages 205-210. (With 9 Plates) Washington Government Printing Office.
- 19. Sheep Catalogue of Beinn Ghreagh, Victoria County, Nova Scotia., 1904. (Folder 5)
  Showing the Origin of the Multi-Nippled Sheep of Beinn Bhreagh, And Giving All the Descendants Down to 1903. Compliments of Alexander Graham Bell. Washington D.C.
- 20. Readings in Line Writing. (Folder 5)
  General note
  Dr. Bell's Copy.
- 21. Bell, Alexander Melville, Visible Speech and Vocal Physiology. The Volta Bureau Washington, D.C.: Press of Gibson Brothers. (Folder 5)
- 22. Proceedings of the Washington Academy of Sciences. vol.8, 9-20, March 4, 1907. (Folder 5)
- 23. Alexander Graham Bell, Aerial Locomotion. Published by the Academy. Washington D.C., 1907. (Folder 4)
- 24. Alexander Graham Bell, Sheep-Breeding Experiments on Beinn Bhreagh. (Folder 4)
  Reprinted from Science, N.S., vol.36 no.925, pp.378-384. September 20, 1912. Compliments of Alexander Graham Bell, 1331 Connecticut Ave. Washington, D.C.
- 25. Alexander Graham Bell, The Inventor of The Electric Speaking Telephone. (Folder 5)
- 26. Alexandre Graham Bell, Le Photophone De La Production Et De La Lumiere; Paris. Gauthier-Villars, Imprimeur-Libraire., 1880. (Folder 4)
- 27. Letter. Alexander Graham Bell to the Attorney-General., October 26, 1885. (Folder 4)
- 28. The Volta Review. Washington, D.C., vol.18 no.4, April 1916. (Folder 4)
- 29. Alexander Graham Bell, Acrical Locomotion with a Few Notes of Progress in the Construction of an Acrodrome. (Folder 4)
  Formerly President of the National Geographic Society (Dr. Bell). Reprinted from the National Geographic Magazine, January 1907. Press of Judd & Detweiler, Incorporated.
- 30. Bell, A. Melville, Pronunzia Inglese Visible. Insegnata. In Dodici Lezioni Catalogue of Works. (Folder 5)
- 31. Photo duplicated manuscripts relating to Bell's parents. Written for the Beinn Bhreagh Recorder, 1912, 1914. (Folder 3)
- 32. Mounted photograph of Alexander Graham Bell. (Folder 6)
- 33. Portrait of Dr. Bell receiving an academic degree; Edinburgh. (Folder 6)
- 34. Alexander Graham Bell, by Catherine Mackenzie., 2 folders. (Folder 2)
  First draft, to be edited and revised. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1928.
- 35. Letter to Alexander Graham Bell from John Macleov, encloses death certificate and receipt in the sum of $10.00., October 27, 1920. (Folder 1)